创世之初 冥冥之中
In the beginning, there was darkness...
随着轰的一声
and then, bang...
诞生了无限膨胀的
giving birth to an endless expanding existence...
时间 空间和物质
of time, space, and matter.
现在 所见超乎我们的想象
Now, see further than we've ever imagined...
超越了我们生存的限制
beyond the limits of our existence...
这个空间我们称之为"宇宙"
in a place we call "The Universe."
外头可能还存在着其它世界...
There may be other worlds out there...
宇宙萌生宇宙
Universes budding off other universes.
那里拷贝不走样
Ewhere there could be an exact copy...
同样是我们的太阳系 我们的地球 我们每一个人
of our solar system, our Earth, and each one of us.
那里 一切都大致相同
Where everything's pretty much the same
或许只有少许不同
or maybe only slightly different.
然而其它宇宙究竟在哪里呢?
But where are these other universes?
为何我们看不到它们呢?
Why can't we see them?
因为我们身处不同的维度里
Because we're in different dimensions.
这可是真的吗?
Can this be true?
如果存在一定尺度和形状的额外的维度
If there are extra dimensions of a certain size and shape...
那么这个实验将会发现它们
this experiment will find them.
问题不在于它们是否存在
The question isn't whether they exist...
而在于它们是否存在一 二 三 四种不同的类型
but whether there's one, two, three, or four different kinds of them.
这种耸人听闻意味着宇宙淹没在浩瀚的平行宇宙之中
This sensationally means the universe sits in a sea of parallel universes.
宇宙:平行宇宙
想象一下另外一个世界 整个宇宙间
Imagine another world, a whole other universe...
其太阳系和行星完全和我们的一模一样
with a solar system and a planet exactly like ours.
在这个平行地球上 居住着你的精确复制品
On this parallel Earth, there lives an exact copy of you.
你可以安享完全相同的人生
You could be leading exactly the same life...
但是是在另一个宇宙里
but in another universe.
现在 想象一下完全独立的宇宙
Now, imagine an entirely separate universe...
你可以过上稍有不同的人生
where you could be living a slightly different life...
就在你度过这辈子的同时
at the same time as you live this life.
这可能看似荒诞 难以置信 不可能的
It may seem fantastic, incredible, and impossible...
但是外头有可能存在着许多其它的宇宙
but there could be many other universes out there.
现在有些世界顶尖的物理学家
And now some of the world's leading physicists...
认为他们有证据来予以证明
believe that they have evidence to prove it.
我们正经历一场存在震撼
We are experiencing an existential shock.
我们的世界观已经被打破
Our worldview has been shattered...
随着对它的认识 对 可以存在平行宇宙
with the realization that, yes, there could be parallel universes.
我的意思是 这只是个搞脑筋的概念
I mean, it's just a mind-boggling idea...
有可能 基本上
that there may be, essentially...
浩瀚的太空中有可能存在着我们的复制品
exact replicas of us out there in the vastness of space.
平行宇宙的概念是我们流行文化的一部分
The idea of a parallel universe is part of our popular culture.
我们周围的人每天都在想它
People all around us think of it every day...
但通常都是虚构
but usually in terms of fiction.
真正令人兴奋的事情之一
One of the real exciting things...
就是如今的科学家正在试图观察
is that scientists today are trying to see...
平行宇宙是不是现实的物理
whether parallel universes are a physical reality.
关于宇宙真是规模的惊人发现
Amazing new discoveries about the true size of the universe...
似乎表明我们所见到的一切
seem to indicate that all that we see...
并非所有的一切
is not all that there is.
我们人类被认为是
We humans have assumed...
把头埋在沙堆里的鸵鸟...
like ostriches with our heads in the sand...
那只是因为我们无法看到某些东西 就以为它不存在
thatjust because we can't see something, it ain't there.
在我祖母还是小姑娘时 举个例子
When my grandma was a little girl, for instance...
他们还不知道还有其它的星系
they still didn't know that there were other galaxies.
现在我们知道了
Now we know that there are...
外头有数以十亿计的星系
billions and billions of other galaxies out there.
显然 存在有四类平行宇宙
Remarkably, there may be four types of parallel universe out there.
一类可能完全等同于我们所在的空间
One kind could exist in the same exact space we're in...
不过它遥不可见 遥不可及
but it is so far away, we cannot see it or reach it.
在另一个脚本里 有多个宇宙
In another scenario, multiple other universes...
可能在巨大的宇宙肥皂泡里
could be in giant cosmic soap bubbles...
漂泊在宇宙泡沫大海里
adrift in a cosmic sea of giant bubbles.
革命性的发展已经改变了整个景观
Revolutionary developments have changed the entire landscape.
来自外层空间的数据让我们对宇宙学有了新的审视
Data from outer space have given us a new look at cosmology...
卫星数据表明可能存在着平行宇宙
and satellite data indicates there could be parallel universes.
在还有一个脚本里 多重平行宇宙
In yet another scenario, many parallel universes...
占用着我们宇宙一模一样的时空
occupy the same space and time as our universe...
然而由于它们处于不同的维度
but because they are in different dimensions...
所以无法看见
they are invisible.
还有脚本 所有的物理定律通通不一样
In yet another, all the laws of physics are different...
所以一切看上去就完全不同了
so everything looks completely different.
新的理论称为弦论
New theories called string theories...
正给我们的世界以更高的维度
are giving us worlds of higher dimensions.
微观尺度上的量子物理学
Quantum physics at the microscopic scale...
同样向我们揭示了这样的事实 平行宇宙有可能存在
is also revealing to us the fact there could be parallel universes.
为了简单起见 物理学家将平行宇宙
To keep things simple, physicists have divided parallel universes...
分成不同的层次
into different levels.
来看看第一层次的平行宇宙
Meet the level-one parallel universe.
按物理学家的说法 第一层次的平行宇宙
According to physicists, the level-one parallel universe...
只是我们宇宙的扩展
is just an extension of our own universe.
那种宇宙
Now, that's the kind of universe...
其实就好象是我们空间
which is really sort of part of our space...
我们巨大空间的组成部分
of our giant space...
不过它太遥远了 我们无法看到
but it's so far away that we can't see it.
第一层次的平行宇宙所基于的概念是
The level-one parallel universe is based on the idea...
宇宙在尺度上是无限的
that the universe is infinite in size.
要真是这样 就凭数学概率就可知
If true, just by the sheer mathematical odds...
在无限的空间里必定存在着
there must be out there in endless space...
一个与我们一模一样的复制品 有太阳系 地球
an exact copy of the solar system, the Earth...
以及地球上所有的人
and all the people on it.
如果你正在筹划远足
If you're planning a trip...
最近的第一层次平行宇宙
the closest level-one parallel universe...
实在是远的难以置信
is really incredibly far away.
实话实说 你必须跑出googolplex码
Crudely speaking, you have to go googolplex yards...
这里 1个googol表示1后面跟着100个0
where a googol is one with a hundred zeroes after it...
而1个googolplex则是1后面跟着1个googol的0
and a googolplex is one with a googol zeroes.
因此这是个恐怖的漫漫长路 远超出我们的视野
So it's an awfully long way, farther than we can see.
那些宇宙极其遥远 连光都到达不了我们这里
Those universes are so far away that light hasn't reached us.
然而我们的宇宙真的是无限的吗?
But is our universe really infinite?
一个新的理论叫做宇宙膨胀说表明就是这回事
A new theory called cosmic inflation suggests that it is.
我们认为它诞生于一个很小很小的结构
We think that it was born in a very, very small state...
然后有一种奇怪的能量
and then there was a kind of a weird energy...
将其推开到一个极大的规模
that pushed it apart by a tremendous amount.
它只管急速膨胀
It just went whoosh.
膨胀解释了我们宇宙在诞生后
Inflation accounts for how our universe...
突然急速长大的原因
suddenly and massively grew after its inception.
我们现在对于空间变得如此之大的的最佳理论
The best theory we have right now for what made space so big--
膨胀说
the theory of inflation--
称 事实上 空间不光巨大
says, in fact, that space isn't just big or huge...
实际上还是无限的
that it's really infinite.
它膨胀无止境
It goes on forever...
这就意味着 不只有1 2 3个
which means that there aren't just one, two, three...
而是有无穷多个空域
but infinitely many other regions of space...
与我们的宇宙一般大
just as big as our universe.
即使是我们所了解的宇宙也是大得出乎意料
Even the universe that we know is mind-blowingly big.
我们在这样的星际空间里翱翔
When we fly around in intergalactic space like this...
你所看到的每一个小不点都可能包含了一个星系
every little blob you see here can contain a galaxy...
以此类推 可能存在着上万亿颗恒星
which, in turn, might contain hundreds of billions of stars...
以及围绕它们的太阳系 等等
with solar systems around them and so on.
所以存在着无数其它空间
So there's just this enormous number of other spaces out there...
我们无法看到
that we can't see.
还不止这些
And there is more.
我们实际上认为存在数量庞大
We actually think that there's a gigantic number...
甚至数量无限的第一层次宇宙
perhaps even an infinite number of level-one universes.
这种激进思想
This radical idea is leading...
正导致宇宙的全新定义
to a completely new definition of the cosmos.
我们常说的宇宙(universe) 其中uni的意思是一
We used to say universe, "uni" meaning one--
一个世界的理论
a one-world theory.
所有一切 我们所见的一切就是宇宙
Everything there is, everything we can see is the universe.
现在 我们有了多重宇宙的概念 存在着无形的世界
Now, we have a multiverse idea where there are unseen worlds--
我们看不见 摸不着的世界
worlds that we cannot see, worlds that we cannot touch.
如果这种想入非非的理论成立 那么后果是耸人听闻的
Ifthis wild theory is correct, the consequences are sensational.
在这个无限宇宙里
Within this infinite universe...
你可能会看到有太阳系
you might have other copies of the solar system...
地球的复制品
of planet Earth.
这确实让人震惊不已
And this is the real shocker.
于是在别的地方有着你
Then there's a copy of me and you...
我以及所有人的复制品
and everyone else out there somewhere.
这还不是全部
And that's not all.
有无限多的其它宇宙 其它地球
There are an infinite number of other universes and other Earths...
我们每个人的无限多的复制品
and infinite copies of each one of us.
要真这样 于是每个生命的每一个 可能的结果必定够已经定局了
Iftrue, then every possible outcome for every life has to happen.
在某些宇宙中 也就是现在所谓的多重宇宙中
In some universes, in what some now call the multiverse...
一个完全掌管着同样的生命
one leads exactly the same life...
而在其它宇宙中 情况会稍有不同
but in others, things can be slightly different.
你不会收到让你烦恼不已的停车罚单
You didn't get that parking ticket that irked you so much...
或者 很不幸 你永远碰不到你的妻子了
or you, unfortunately, never met your wife.
一切都完全有可能实际发生在
Anything that is physically possible actually does occur...
其他一些平行宇宙中
in some other parallel universe.
这意味着在某个宇宙中 猫王还活着
It means that in one universe, Elvis Presley is still alive.
在另一个第一层次宇宙中
In a different level-one universe...
小布什是个棒球大联盟专员
George W. Bush is the baseball commissioner.
或许在某些宇宙中 我们根本就不存在
Or perhaps we don't exist at all in some of these universes.
结果令人震惊
The implications are staggering.
如果宇宙是无限的
And if the universe is infinite...
所有这些第一层次的宇宙真的存在于
and there really are all these level-one universes...
无限多重宇宙中的话
in the infinite multiverse...
那么所有这些可能性确实会发生的
all those other possibilities did somewhere happen.
学术上 有两个方法计算出
Technically, there are a couple of ways mathematically...
宇宙确实是无限的
for the universe to be truly infinite...
但是 基本上 它必须表现出是扁平的
but, essentially, it must be shown to be flat.
宇宙似乎是非常平的
The universe seems to be perfectly flat...
这意味着宇宙要么是平的
which means either the universe is flat...
要么是弯曲极其细微 我们难以觉察
or is curved so slightly that we can't see it.
要是这样 宇宙最终会自我折回
In this case, the universe would eventually curve back in on itself...
形成一个球形
and form a hypersphere.
于是它在尺度和体积上是有限的
It would then be finite in size and volume...
并不是扁平和无限的
and not flat and infinite.
另一个角度来看
Another way to look at this is that the universe...
宇宙有可能已经膨胀得非常快速 非常巨大
may have inflated so quickly and so enormously...
以至于看上去只是平平的
that it only looks flat.
想想虫子在巨大的气球上爬行
Think of a bug walking on a gigantic balloon.
气球越大 看上去就越平
The larger the balloon, the flatter things get.
虫子往四处爬行 说道
The bug walks in any direction, and the bug says...
啊 宇宙在我看来完全是平的
"Well, the universe seems perfectly flat to me."
但是从远处看去
But from a distance...
我们看到了虫子爬行在巨大的气球上
we see that the bug is walking on a gigantic balloon.
不过现在有了一个了不起的新工具
But now an amazing new tool...
威尔金森微波各向异性探测器 (WMAP)
the Wilkinson Microwave Anisotropy Probe or WMAP...
正在改变一切
is changing everything.
有人称 非凡的图像揭示了宇宙的真实形状
Some say the remarkable images reveal the true shape of the universe.
我们现在看到的是宇宙的婴儿照片
What we have here are baby pictures of the universe...
拍自它40万岁时
what it looked like when it was only 400,000 years old.
我们回眸时间如此久远
We're looking so far back in time...
星系都尚未形成
that the galaxies hadn't even formed yet.
我们只见死气腾腾 弥漫的气体 它随着时间推移
We just had this dead, diffuse gas which, gradually, over time...
逐渐堆聚成星系 恒星 行星
clumped into galaxies, stars, planets.
WMAP捕捉到的是宇宙最早的迹象
The WMAP is catching the very earliest signs of creation.
据称 其任务就是测量大爆炸
Officially, it is tasked with measuring radiation...
残留的辐射
left over from the Big Bang.
不过现在有些科学家设计了一个实验
But now some scientists have devised an experiment...
来估算宇宙的整体形状
to calculate the overall shape of the universe.
如果我将光射向空间
Ifl send light rays through space...
形成一个大三角 从我们这里发射出去
and make a gigantic triangle, going from us here...
射向我们所看到的最边缘 然后返回
out to the farthest edges of what we can see and then back...
它们的角度
the angles of those--
那个三角形加起来应该正好等于180度
that triangle should add up to exactly 180 degrees.
如果宇宙如气球那样弯曲
Ifthe universe is curved like a balloon...
大三角的角度加起来
the angles of the giant triangle would add up...
就会大于180度
to more than 180 degrees.
为了发现宇宙是扁平的还是弯曲的
To find out if the universe is flat or curved...
他们将激光束射向太空
they shot laser beams deep into space...
形成一个巨大的三角形
and made a giant light triangle.
我们现在可以说 测量有了结果
Now we can tell, and the measurement is in...
答案是 其工作出色
and the answer is, it works beautifully.
角度加起来刚好180度
The angles add up to exactly 180 degrees.
宇宙是平的
The universe is flat.
WMAP似乎表明宇宙是平的
The WMAP seems to show that the universe is flat.
对某些人来说 不管怎样 评判依然
For some, however, the jury is still out...
纠结于扁平宇宙的问题
on the flat universe question.
我倾向于认为宇宙事实上是
I tend to think that the universe is, in fact...
某种肥皂泡 不过其弯曲非常细微 我们无法感觉到而已
a soap bubble of some sort, but it is bent so slightly that we can't see it.
有些专家称 还存在着
Some experts say that there are other...
更加莫名其妙的平行宇宙
even more mind-boggling kinds of parallel universes out there...
第二层次的平行宇宙
a level-two type parallel universe...
是由漂浮在多维空间里的巨大的宇宙肥皂泡构成的
made up of giant, cosmic soap bubbles that float in hyperspace.
每个单独的泡沫里都有一个完整的宇宙
Each independent bubble has within it an entire universe.
问题是 我们是否就处在一个巨大的宇宙泡里呢?
The question is, do we all really live in a giant cosmic bubble?
难道我们宇宙就处在
Could our universe be just one mega bubble...
一大堆宇宙巨泡中的一个里吗?
in a cosmic crowd of mega bubbles?
如果耸人听闻的第二层次平行宇宙的概念是对的话
If the sensational, level-two type parallel universe idea is right...
那么宇宙的真实属性
then the true nature of the cosmos...
将更为惊人 超乎想象
could be even more astonishing than ever imagined.
惊人的想法就是在活生生的宇宙中
The amazing concept is that in the instance of creation...
我们的宇宙迅速 突然 大规模地膨胀
our universe rapidly, suddenly, and massively inflated...
形成了一个巨大的宇宙肥皂泡
creating a giant cosmic soap bubble.
我们这独特的宇宙漂浮在汹涌的
Our unique universe floats in a seething sea...
其它超级巨泡的大海里
of other super-bubbles...
泡泡会发生碰撞
where bubbles can clash...
产下新生的宇宙
and spawn baby brother and sister universes.
一直这样进行下去
It's happening all the time.
宇宙一直在膨胀 炸开
Universes are inflating, popping out...
于是这些巨大的宇宙爆发了
and then blowing up to these huge sizes of universes.
这些第二层次的泡泡所在的介质
The medium these level-two bubbles are floating in...
有些人称之为体宇宙 而其他人则称之为多维空间
is what some call the bulk and others call hyperspace.
在这个新模式里
In this new paradigm...
肥皂泡可以形成 再形成 可以破裂
soap bubbles can form, re-form, they can split.
它是动态的: 宇宙可以无中生有
It's dynamic: universes being created out of nothing...
宇宙可以萌生出别的宇宙
universes budding off other universes.
总之 这些泡泡构成了第二层次平行宇宙
Altogether, these bubbles form the level-two type parallel universe.
其中 存在着数量无限的
And within it, there are an infinite number...
第一层次平行宇宙
of level-one type parallel universes.
第一层次和第二层次平行宇宙
The level-one and level-two universes...
都处在我们同一个空间里
are all in our same one space.
只有一个空间
There's only one space.
这些不同的区域
Then there are these different regions...
我们管它们叫做第一层次和第二层次平行宇宙
which we call level-one and level-two parallel universes.
穿越第二层次平行宇宙
A fly-by through the level-two parallel universe...
某些人也会管它叫多元宇宙
or what some also call the multiverse...
那将是一场可怕而壮观的体验
would be a terrifying and spectacular experience.
多元宇宙中的宇宙 个个都是来也匆匆
A multiverse of universes, each one popping into existence...
去也匆匆 也许在彼此相撞
popping out of existence, perhaps colliding with each other.
走出灾难 迎来生机
Out of calamity comes existence.
我们所谓的第二层次多元宇宙
What we call the level-two multiverse...
其实最好将其看作是树或分形结构
is really best thought of as a tree or a fractal structure...
你可以看到空域在疯长
where you have a region of space expanding like crazy...
和其它空域交织在一起
and spiraling off other regions...
然后又膨胀 交织上其它的空域
which then expand, spiraling off other regions.
其它空域会依附它萌生
And other ones can bud off of that.
所以你可以看到这种杂乱 宇宙永恒的分形
So you can get this chaotic, eternally branching set of universes...
依附它们的前辈而萌发出来
budding off from their predecessors.
这个多元宇宙里的宇宙无限组合
An infinite set of universes in this multiverse.
这个宏伟过程的专业术语叫做气泡成核
The big term for this monumental process is bubble nucleation.
气泡成核是极客创造的短语
Bubble nucleation is the geek-speech phrase...
其所形容的过程 就是你看到奇怪物质在膨胀
for the process where you have this inflating strange material...
然后有那么一块停止了膨胀
and then a little piece of it stops inflating...
引起其周围的泡沫状空域
and causes a bubble-shaped region expanding around it...
也停止了膨胀
to also stop inflating...
于是你在这个泡泡里创造出了 一片优雅 宁静的空域
and then you create in this bubble a nice, calm region of space...
你最终在那里形成了星系 恒星 行星
where you will eventually form galaxies, stars, planets...
乃至我们这样的人类
and even people like us.
所以我们都是泡泡的孩子
So we are the children of the bubble.
人类有史以来第一次
For the first time in human history...
泡泡的孩子正凝视着
children of the bubble are peering out...
观察着平行宇宙
and seeing on the horizon parallel universes.
物理学家坚持认为他们现在已经有望
Determined physicists believe they are now on the brink...
揭开宇宙终极之谜了
of uncovering the ultimate mysteries of the universe.
为何要寻找这些我们触摸不到的平行宇宙呢?
Why look for these parallel universes that we can't touch?
因为它们掌握着秘密中的秘密
Because they hold the secret of secrets.
它们掌握着万物的起源之谜
They hold the secret of the origin of everything there is.
有史以来第一次 我们可以想象我们宇宙本身的出身
For the first time, we can imagine where our universe itseIfcame from.
也许我们的宇宙突然诞生于
Perhaps when our universe popped into existence...
与另一个平行宇宙的碰撞
colliding with another parallel universe...
也许是萌生于另一个宇宙
perhaps budding from another universe...
这些就是现代研究的课题:
these are the stuff of modern research today:
前大爆炸物理学
pre-Big Bang physics.
创世之前的物理学
Physics before Genesis.
但是存在着一个问题
But there is a problem.
几十年来 科学家一直在探索
For decades, scientists have been searching...
一个整体的万有理论
for one cohesive theory of everything...
一个结合起爱因斯坦的广义相对论
one to unite Einstein's theory of general relativity...
它解释了大尺度上的引力作用
which explains how gravity works over large scales...
和量子物理学 最小物质的科学
with quantum physics, the science of the tiniest matter.
结合在一起 这两个伟大的理论来解释
Together, these two great theories explain...
人类对于宇宙迄今所知的一切
everything humanity knows so far about the cosmos.
但是犹如卡通片 猫和老鼠
But like a cartoon cat and mouse...
它们相互冲突
They are at war with one another.
这两个理论相互敌视
These two theories hate each other.
它们完全不协调 不买账
They're completely inconsistent, incompatible.
无法了解如今的世界
No way to understand in today's world...
量子版的广义相对论
a quantum version of general relativity.
我们能否来一个强迫婚姻
How can we get a shotgun marriage...
把这两个互不喜欢的理论拉在一起呢?
between these two theories that don't like each other?
把它们拉在一起
Bringing those together would give you...
会给你带来万有理论一定意义上
a theory of everything in the sense...
那些就是你所需要的配料 我想
that those are the ingredients you would need, I think...
以了解大爆炸
to understand the Big Bang...
以了解宇宙的起源
to understand the origin of the universe.
想当初 1980年代 科学家提出了
When, in the 1980s, scientists came up with...
一个悦耳动听的概念 弦论
a lyrical-sounding idea, string theory...
它承诺可以解决宇宙间所有的奥秘
it promised to solve all the mysteries of the universe...
包括平行宇宙是否真的存在
including whether or not parallel universes are real.
其概念是所有的粒子
The idea is that all particles are not solid points or dots...
并不是科学所说的一定的点
as science said they were.
相反 如果你靠近观察
Instead, if you could see up close...
粒子事实上是细微的弦状的物体
particles are, in fact, tiny string-like objects...
各自以不同的方式在振动
that individually vibrate in various ways.
弦论从振动的弦的概念出发
String theory starts out by taking the idea of a string which vibrates...
产生出各种粒子 并由此产生物理学
giving rise to different particles, and doing physics with that.
某种程度 它相当于音乐
That's rather musical, in a way.
就像是乐队里的吉他和低音
It's like using guitar and bass in a band...
通过弦的振动产生出各种音符
to generate different notes from vibrations of strings.
随着科学家探讨弦论的深入
As scientists explored string theory more closely...
他们得到了惊人的发现
they made a remarkable discovery.
我们发现
We found that it wasn't just strings...
不只是弦牵涉到了物理学
that were involved in the physics...
而且还涉及了膜以及其它扩展的东西
but also membranes and other extended objects...
它们都是会振动的
which could vibrate.
这有点像扩大的乐队
And that's rather like enlarging the band...
增加了鼓和其它乐器
to have drums and other instruments...
丰富了音色
which enrich the sound...
真正扩展了可以演奏的节目
and really broaden the repertoire of things that could be played.
弦论现在已经演变成了M理论
String theory has now evolved into what is called...
即膜理论
"M" or membrane theory.
所以我们现在我们已经意识到了 我们实际所见的粒子 宇宙本身
So now we realize that the particles we see in nature, the universe itself...
都是由振动的膜和振动的弦构成的
consists of vibrating membranes and vibrating strings.
M理论最高成就来自
The crowning achievement of M-theory came...
当时科学家意识到为了搞明白一切
when scientists realized that, to make sense of everything...
你就需要考虑宇宙存在着11个维度
you need to think of the universe as existing in 11 dimensions.
如果你坐在山顶
Ifyou're sitting on a mountaintop...
看下去 你可以看到所有单独的小村落
and you look down, you can see all the separate little villages...
它们根本不是整齐划一的
that are not unified at all.
但是站在山顶 你看到的是一幅连贯整体的美丽景象
But from a mountaintop, you look at a coherent, whole, beautiful picture.
那就是M理论
And that's M-theory.
M理论解释了宇宙活动中
M-theory explains how the tiniest...
最小以及最大的东西
as well as the biggest things in the cosmos work.
它同时指出我们都处于一个巨大而充满活力的膜上
It also proposes that we all live on a giant and energetic membrane.
我们的宇宙被限定在这个无形的额外维度的墙内
Our universe is tethered to this wall by invisible extra dimensions.
为了把事情搞得更加荒唐 M理论提出
To make matters crazier, M-theory proposes...
那六到七个我们日常
that six or seven of these dimensions...
感觉不到的额外的维度
the extra ones we don't sense every day...
是极小的 就在你面前
are tiny and right in front of your nose.
在每个人所经过的所有点上
At every point of any one of these people walking by...
你会挑选一个点 在那个点上
you pick a point, at that point...
将存在着极其细微
there will be an incredibly tiny, curled-up...
卷曲着六到七个维度 你只是没察觉而已
either six or seven dimensions that you just don't perceive.
这些膜也彼此非常贴近
These membranes are also very close to each other.
你可以看到这些膜中的一个构成了一个宇宙
You could have one of these membranes being a universe.
然后 侧向移动
And then, moving sideways...
你可以看到另一个膜 也是一个独立的宇宙
you have another membrane being a separate universe...
它们之间相隔只有1到2毫米
and they may be just a millimeter or two away.
充满活力的物质巨墙并排漂浮
The giant walls of energetic matter float side by side...
就像体宇宙或多维空间里的巨大的床单
like humongous sheets in the bulk or in hyperspace.
整个宇宙有可能依附在膜上
An entire universe may be attached to a brane...
或者是宇宙可以整个占据另一个宇宙
or a universe can occupy the whole of another one.
我们这个宇宙就坐落在这些巨大的膜的表皮
Our own universe sits on the skin of one of these giant branes...
从而漂浮在茫茫宇宙空间大海之中
that, in turn, is adrift in the cosmic sea of space.
它漂浮在一个更大的结构里 那叫做体宇宙
And it's floating around in a bigger structure called the bulk.
我们的三维宇宙就像是一个膜
Our three-dimensional universe is like a membrane...
漂浮在这个更大的结构里
floating around within this larger structure.
相信无形的额外的维度
Believing that invisible extra dimensions...
就像是脐带 将我们与巨大的膜所在的
that, like an umbilical cord, connect us...
多维宇宙或体宇宙联系在一起
to a hyper or bulk space where giant membranes live...
是需要信仰的一个飞跃的
demands a huge leap of faith.
我们所依附的这些膜又在哪里呢?
Where are these membranes that we're stuck to?
为何我们看不到与我们关联的这些维度呢?
And why can't we see these extra dimensions that connect us?
我坐在这只皮艇 漂浮在海面上
I'm floating around here on this kayak on the surface of the ocean...
你可以将它视为一个二维的面
and you can think of this as a two-dimensional surface.
但是在我下方 存在着完全不同的维度
But below me, there's a whole 'nother dimension.
下面的维度里 就是鱼儿居住的地方
There's the down dimension where all the fish live.
你可以将其视为体宇宙
You can think of that as the bulk.
我漂浮在一个膜上
I'm on a membrane, floating around...
而体宇宙就是另一个维度
and the bulk is the other dimension.
水面之下的鱼相对我
The fish down below the surface of the water...
是在另一个维度里
are in a different dimension than I am.
它们甚至不知道我在这里
They don't even know that I'm here...
除非我碰巧划桨击中它们
unless I happen to splash around and hit one on the head...
等等之类
or something like that.
因此它们有可能完全无视我的存在
So they might be completely oblivious to my existence...
我也可能完全无视它们的存在
and I could be oblivious to their existence...
因为我们处于不同的维度里
because we're in different dimensions.
然而能否短暂思绪一下 把你送入一个额外的维度里
But can a fleeting thought send you into an extra dimension...
送入一个平行宇宙呢?
and on to a parallel universe?
根据最新的M理论 刹那间
According to the latest M-theory, in less than an instant...
在不足兆兆分之一秒的时间里
in the first trillionth of a trillionth of a second...
前宇宙里的膜 就像是巨大的钹
membranes in a pre-universe cosmos, like gigantic cosmic cymbals...
相互碰撞 产生了大爆炸
smashed together and produced the Big Bang.
经过了近137亿年的光阴
Over almost 13.7 billion years...
一个巨大的不断膨胀的原始物质泡
a huge expanding bubble of primordial matter...
演变成了我们现在多了解和热爱的宇宙
evolved into the universe we now know and love.
膜的碰撞也能够产生平行宇宙吗?
Can crashing membranes create parallel universes, too?
如果曾经发生过 那么就可能再次发生
If it happened once, it can happen again...
一而再 再而三
and again and again.
因此有可能是个循环
So it's possible that there's a continuous cycle...
膜相互碰撞产生宇宙
of branes smashing together to produce universes...
永不停止
and that it never stops.
要真是这样 第二层次平行宇宙就必定存在
If this is true, level-two parallel universes must exist.
时间永续
Time goes on forever...
宇宙灾难所带来的宇宙
and there's a continual process of birth of universes...
诞生过程也持续不断
through cosmic catastrophes.
在第三层次里
In the level-three type...
平行宇宙的诞生方式将更加怪异
there is an even more fantastic way parallel universes can form.
来看一下它的运作
Here's how it works.
在第一和第二层次里
In both the level-one and level-two kinds...
存在着独立的宇宙
there are replica universes separated from us...
复制着我们此时此地的时空
in the here and now by time and space...
但是在第三层次平行宇宙中
but in the level-three parallel universe...
我们的复制品就在此时此地
these copies of us are right here, right now...
在我们同一个时空里
living in the exact same space and time.
他们独立于我们
They are separated from us...
因为他们处在同一个空间的不同的维度里
because they're in a different dimension of this same space.
来更集中一下我们的思想 他们的数量无限
And to bend our minds more, there are an infinite number of them.
如果属实 这个倍具争议的"多世界"概念
If true, this controversial "many worlds" concept...
将意义重大
has monumental consequences.
平行宇宙并不存在
Parallel universes don't exist.
对 他们是在胡说八道
- Right. - They're nonsense.
它们是《阴阳魔界》里的东西
They're something out of a "Twilight Zone" episode...
是糟糕的《星际迷航》的再现
a bad "Star Trek" rerun.
但是你忘了一件事
But you forget one thing.
一个小小的量子差异可以将我独立于
One small quantum difference could separate me...
一个完全不同的宇宙
from an entirely different universe...
在那里 有我的多重拷贝
where I have multiple copies of myself...
过着多重不同的人生
leading multiple different lives.
着够惊人的
This is shocking.
这甚至影响到了道德规范
This even affects morals.
我的意思是 我为何要守法
I mean, why should l obey the law...
一旦得知在某些宇宙中 我犯了罪
knowing that in some universe, if I commit a crime...
我想逃脱处罚
I'm going to get away with it?
无耻的想法出自奇异的世界
The outrageous idea comes from the strange world...
量子力学
of quantum mechanics...
原子的科学
the science of the atom.
在奇异的原子世界里
In the bizarre atomic world...
我们看到电子完全消失了
we have electrons that literally disappear...
在其它地方重现
reappear someplace else.
电子可以同时在多个地方
Electrons that could be multiple places at the same time.
这种惊人的量子力学现象
This staggering quantum mechanical phenomenon...
被载入了海森堡的测不准原理
is enshrined in the Heisenberg uncertainty principle.
听上去很荒谬 不仅是量子物理
As crazy as it sounds, not only does quantum physics...
告诉你 一个小小的粒子可以同时在两个地方
tell you that a little particle can be in two places at once...
而且海森堡的测不准原理
but the so-called Heisenberg uncertainty principle...
还告诉你有时粒子
tells you that sometime the particle...
还必须同时在两个地方
even must be in two places at once.
用激光和玻璃苹果
With a laser light and a glass apple...
就可以让你看到光粒子即光子是如何做到的
it can be seen how light particles, or photons, do this.
可以看到光子
This shows that photons...
我激光笔射出的小小的光粒子
the little particles of light coming out of my laser...
可以同时到达几个地方
can end up in several places at once.
由于我们是由小粒子构成的
And since we are made of little particles...
这就意味着 要是它们能同时在几个地方
that means if they can be in several places at once...
那么我们也可以的
so can we.
换句话说 在你短暂思绪的片刻间
In other words, in the instant that you have a fleeting thought...
你整个身子飞跃进了另一个维度
your whole body makes a quantum leap...
飞跃进了平行宇宙
into another dimension and into a parallel universe.
那意味着 如果我走在路上
And what it means is that if I am walking down the pavement...
仓促做个决定
and just make a snap decision...
究竟是往左还是往右走
as to whether I'm going to go left or right...
如果我的决定
if my decision depends...
是依靠我大脑里的粒子来做的话
on what some little particle in my brain was doing...
那么我最终的决定会是两个方向都去
then l will actually end up doing both...
我的生命
and the life of mine--
它实际上分开进入了两个平行的现实
it effectively splits into two parallel realities.
在第三层次平行宇宙中
In a level-three type parallel universe...
甚至猫都不止九条命
even a cat has many more than nine lives.
问题是 在某些世界里
The trouble is, in some of these worlds...
猫可能已经死去了
the cat could be dead.
同时 在其他平行宇宙里
And at the same time, in other parallel universes...
同样的猫可以活得活蹦乱跳
the same cat can be alive and kicking.
怎么回事?
But how?
你怎么可以有死猫与活猫同时存在?
How can you have a dead cat and a live cat simultaneously?
因为宇宙分成了两半
Because the universe splits in half.
在一个宇宙里 我们看到了死猫
In one universe, we have a dead cat.
而在另一个宇宙里 我们看到了活猫
In the other universe, we have a live cat.
适应它吧
Get used to it.
更惊人的是
What is even more shocking...
在这许多世界中的某些里
is that in some of these many worlds...
一个细微的量子差异被认为可以改变整个世界
a tiny quantum difference in thought can change the whole world.
这就像蝴蝶扇动翅膀 可以产生飓风一样
It's like the butterfly that flaps its wing and makes the hurricane.
细小的微观事件可以改变历史的进程
Tiny microscopic events would change the course of history.
因此 每一个历史事件实际上
So every historical event actually happened...
就是尽一切可能发生在这个不断分叉的
in every possible way in some branch...
多重宇宙的某些分支上的结果
of this ever-splitting, many-worlds universe.
在其中一个宇宙里 希特勒的纳粹党赢得了二次世界大战
In one,the Nazis Won World War II
如果是那样 我在这里讲的就是德语
In which case,I'm now speaking German
而且在我后面将会有一个纳粹党的标志
and there's a Swastika behind me.
而在另一个世界里
In another world
没有发生那样可怕的事
none of the horror ever happened
在宇宙中 也没有第二次世界大战
In one universe,there's no World war II
而且 也不会有五千万人无辜的死掉
and 50 or so million people didn't have to die.
宛如转个不停的骰子 各种数字皆有可能
Like the endless rolls of the dice, all possible numbers...
各种宇宙皆有可能
and all possible kinds of universes and outcomes...
最终的结果会出现在这多重世界中的一个
will eventually turn up and occur in one of these many worlds.
事实上 我们所有的愿望也都会在
In fact, all our wishes, too, can come true...
平行宇宙中成真
in a parallel universe.
假如多重世界的概念是正确的话
If the many worlds idea is right...
就会在宇宙的一个分支上
then there's a branch of the universe...
芝加哥小熊队夺得了去年职棒锦标赛的冠军
in which the Chicago Cubs won the World Series last year.
你可以想象美国还是英国的殖民地
You can imagine that the USA was still a colony...
举个例子
of the British, for example.
甚至行不通的都可能发生在某些平行宇宙中
Even the impossible is probable in some parallel universe.
甚至会有来到我们世界的生物
There could even be creatures coming into our world...
是来自这些神秘的额外维度
from these mysterious extra dimensions.
听起来有点搞脑筋
As mind-boggling as it sounds...
只要说起惊人的平行宇宙
when it comes to the amazing world of parallel universes...
任何事情都可能发生 已经发生 或将发生
anything that can happen has happened or will happen...
在其它的宇宙间
in some other universe...
其它的维度里 其它的时空里
in some other dimension, space, and time.
量子差异可以改写历史
Quantum differences can rewrite history...
创造多重宇宙
creating multiple universes...
每个都有着不同的疯狂结果
each with wildly different outcomes...
在那里 一切皆有可能
where anything and everything is possible.
有些战争就从来没发生过
Some wars never happened.
其它 我们就永远想象不出了
Others we never imagined did.
细微的变化意味着与彗星失之交臂
A slight change means a comet missed...
恐龙依然横行在地球上的某些地方
and even dinosaurs still roam some Earth somewhere.
所有这些怪异的平行宇宙无一例外
All and every one of these fantastic parallel universes...
都占据着同一个空间
occupy the same space...
但是各自都处于不同的维度中 所以我们是看不见的
but are in a different dimension, and so invisible to us.
在你安静地看电视时
Even as you peacefully watch TV...
整个其它看不见的世界有可能在你周围为所欲为
whole other invisible worlds could be raging all around you.
这些平行宇宙就在你的客厅里
These parallel universes are in your living room.
也就是说 在你的客厅里 有恐龙
This means that in your living room, there are dinosaurs.
你听不见它们
You can't hear them.
你看不见恐龙
You can't see the dinosaurs...
在你的客厅里横冲直撞
that are rampaging throughout your living room...
但是它们就在这里
but they're there.
将每个人创造出N多版本的量子法则
The quantum principle that creates many versions of each person...
同样也可以创造出全部宇宙
can also create entire universes.
宇宙 一定程度上 实际上比电子还要小
The universe, at one point, was actually smaller than an electron.
如果真是这样 如果电子确如描述的那样
If that's true and if electrons are described...
以平行状态同时处于许多地方的话
by being many places at the same time in parallel states...
这就意味着宇宙也同样以平行状态存在着
this means that the universe also exists in parallel states.
你不可避免地遇到平行宇宙
You inevitably get parallel universes.
这是别无选择的
There's no choice.
然而这还不是全部
But that's not all.
科学家最近再次震惊了世界
Scientists recently have shocked the world again...
声称可能存在着不止一种平行宇宙
and claimed that there could be one more kind of parallel universe.
这第四类平行宇宙的产生原因
These level-four type are created...
既有量子起伏 也有膜之间的碰撞
either by quantum fluctuations or by branes clashing.
其产生是全然不同的
What is created is radically different.
在这类平行宇宙中 所有的规则通通不管用了
In this type of parallel universe, all the rules are out the window.
它有可能 事实上
It could be, in fact...
数学与物理实际所描述的
that the mathematics and physics describing reality...
不同于我们宇宙中的情况
differs from what we're used to in our universe.
如果物理定律在第四层次平行宇宙中完全不同的话
If the laws of physics are different in a level-four parallel universe...
空间可能就存在于气体和粒子中
space could just consist of gas and particles.
星系 恒星 行星就不会形成
Galaxies, stars, and planets would not have formed...
我们所知的生命也不会存在
and life as we know it would not exist.
为了证明各种平行宇宙
To show that any type of parallel universe...
层次一 二 三 四的存在
level one, two, three or four, truly exists...
专家们必须找到证据
experts must find the evidence.
无论其很大 很小还是不可见
Be they big, tiny or invisible...
科学家必须找到额外维度的
scientists must find physical indications...
物理迹象
of the extra dimensions...
并被认为是将我们和其它世界联系在一起的
that supposedly connect us to these other worlds.
为此 伊利诺斯费米实验室的科学家如今
To do it, today physicists at Fermilab in lllinois...
正在进行特别的实验
are conducting extraordinary experiments...
希望证明各种
hoping to prove that any kind...
甚至最荒诞的平行宇宙真的存在
even the wildest type of parallel universe, is really out there.
有史以来第一次 实实在在的引人注目的实验
For the first time ever, real and remarkable experiments...
正发生在费米实验室之类的粒子加速器里
are taking place at particle colliders like the Tevatron at Fermilab.
眼下 这台粒子加速器正在寻找
Right now, this detector is looking for evidence...
额外维度的证据
of extra dimensions.
如果额外维度具有一定的尺度和形状
Ifthere are extra dimensions of a certain size and shape...
那么这个实验就会发现的
this experiment will find them.
他们揭示额外维度的最佳机会
Their best chance of exposing extra dimensions...
来自将微粒子
comes from smashing microscopic particles together...
以超高速相碰撞
at super speeds.
证据就是引力
The smoking gun in the hunt is gravity.
它已被证明是独特的弱力
It has been found to be a uniquely weak force...
因此费米实验室的物理学家们正在寻找携带引力的粒子
so the Fermilab physicists are looking for the particle that carries gravity.
它就是所谓的引力子
It is called a graviton.
它是携带引力的粒子
It's the particle that carries gravity...
我们认为它掌握了空间的所有的额外维度
which we think knows about all of the extra dimensions of space.
所以我们认为引力子
So we think the gravitons...
如果你可以用高能量来产生它们的话
if you can produce them in high energies...
那么实际上它们也应该会消失在额外维度中的
should actually move off into the extra dimensions.
但是发现引力子 或至少发现其踪迹
But finding a graviton, or at least a sign of one...
是个巨大的挑战
is a huge challenge.
它棘手而复杂 因为你是在寻找没有的东西
It's tricky and complicated because you're looking for nothing.
你是在寻找已经消失了的东西
You're looking for something that has disappeared.
现在的速度是多少?
What's the rate now?
你要找到一个奇异的粒子是异常罕见的
It's very, very rare that you make a really exotic particle.
因此我们确实必须碰撞数十亿次
So we literally have to collide them billions of times...
以发现非常罕见的事件
in order to find the very rare event...
你才可能看到粒子之类的东西
where you make something like a particle...
消失在额外维度中
that disappears into extra dimensions.
正负质子对撞机发射质子和反质子
The Tevatron collider shoots miniscule protons and antiprotons...
惊人的速度几乎达到了光速
at terrific speeds just short of the speed of light...
运行在4英里长 钢铁包裹的超导环里
around a four-mile-long, super-enforced, steel-encased ring.
为了敏感的实验设备不受地表噪音的干扰
To protect the sensitive experiments from surface noise...
同时为了安全起见
and for safety reasons...
碰撞环被安置于地下深处
the collision ring lies deep underground.
我们将高能质子束沿着大环的一个方向运行
We take beams of high-energy protons going one way around a big ring...
将高能反质子束沿着环的另一个方向运行
and a beam of high-energy antiprotons going the other way around the ring...
然后 在圆环的两个地方 将两者对撞在一起
and then, at two places in the ring, we smash them together.
强烈的对撞会湮灭粒子
The mighty collision annihilates the particles...
产生剧烈的能量球
and produces an intense ball of pure energy...
其想法就是 我们也许会产生新的粒子
The idea being that perhaps we can make new particles...
消失在额外维度中
that disappear into the extra dimensions.
假如什么事都没有 科学家如何知道
Ifnothing happens, how will the scientists know...
引力子已经消失在了额外的维度中了呢?
that a graviton has moved off into an extra dimension?
你所说的方法就是通过重建一切
The way that you tell that is by reconstructing...
除了这个乱七八糟的对撞产生的东西
everything else that happened in this messy collision...
于是就会说 噢 有一些能量
and then saying, "Oops, there's some energy...
和动能消失了
"and momentum that's missing here."
我们称此为缺失能量搜寻
So we call this a missing energy search.
这可能用上几年 数十亿次的对撞
It could take years and billions of collisions...
才会得到历史性的发现 找到更高的维度
before history happens and higher dimensions are found.
如果额外维度真的存在 那就意味着宇宙
If extra dimensions are there, it means the universe...
是一个出奇的大 出奇陌生的空间
is a much bigger and much stranger place...
远超出我们的想象
than we have ever imagined.
不过要真是这样 那就无可厚非地
But if it does happen, it would be proof positive...
证明了平行宇宙的存在了
that parallel worlds exist.
接下来的问题将是我们如何去那里呢?
The question then will be, how do we get there?
面对遥远未来的灭绝
Faced with extinction in the far-flung future...
人类能否打开平行宇宙的大门呢?
can humankind open a portal to a parallel universe?
平行宇宙不只是一个疯狂的概念
Parallel universes are not just a crazy idea...
物理学家将科学与幻想结合的梦想
dreamed up by physicists to marry science with fiction.
如果最终证明其存在
If finally proven to exist...
它们在遥远的未来就具有重要的
they could have an important practical purpose...
实际用途
in the far-off future.
找到通往另一个世界的通道可以有朝一日拯救人类
Finding a tunnel to another world could one day save humanity.
数十亿年后
Billions of years from now...
我们地球必将一命呜呼
our Earth will meet its inevitable demise.
专家们称 它不是死于大崩塌就是死于大冻结
Experts say that it will all end either in a big crunch or big freeze.
要是其它宇宙被证明存在
If other universes are shown to exist...
有人称它们可以作为某种宇宙救生艇
some say they could serve as a kind of cosmic lifeboat.
对于未来的人类
For a future generation...
通往另一个世界的通道或关卡
a passage or gateway to another world...
可能就是他们生存的唯一希望所在
could be their only hope for survival.
问题是 我们能否找到通往那里的通道
The question is, can we find a way to get there?
一个理论上从我们宇宙前往另一个宇宙的绝妙方法
One cool way of theoretically going from our universe to another one...
就是通过所谓的虫洞
is to go through what's called a wormhole...
连接两个宇宙之桥
a bridge connecting two universes...
就好像坐上火车或地铁
kind of like getting on a train or a subway.
犹如城市里的地铁系统
Like a subway system in a city...
经过隧道去另一个地方
going through this tunnel to a different place.
想象有两张纸
Think of two sheets of paper...
相互平行
that are stacked parallel to each other...
然后想象有一个通道 一条捷径
but then think of a gateway, a shortcut...
一个门户连接着这两个宇宙
a portal connecting these two universes.
这个极端的想法早在1935年就提出了
This extreme idea was first proposed back in 1935...
是无与伦比的爱因斯坦和他的学生罗森提出的
by the inimitable Albert Einstein and his student, Nathan Rosen.
连接两个黑洞的咽喉 理论上
A "throat" with two conjoined black holes, theoretically...
可以允许某些人 和地铁上的乘客一样
allows someone, like a passenger on a subway train...
快速前往另一个时空
to quickly travel to another space and time.
这可能有效 前提是宇宙真的是无限多元宇宙
This could work if the universe is really an infinite multiverse.
当然 这在理论上是可能的捷径
Certainly, it's a theoretical possibility...
可以这么说
a sort of shortcut, if you like.
它承认宇宙间的
And it allows the possibility of traveling...
远距离穿行
between distant parts of the universe...
乃至不同宇宙间穿行的可能性
or perhaps between different universes.
企图穿越虫洞存在各种各样的问题
There are all sorts of problems with trying to traverse a wormhole.
不过首当其冲的挑战貌似无法逾越
But one challenge above all seems insurmountable.
当年爱因斯坦将虫洞引进他的方程式时
When Einstein introduced the wormhole into his equations...
他不认为有人能
he didn't think that anyone...
穿越这些东西
could ever walk through one of these things...
因为 说到底 你会命丧这个过程的
because, after all, you die in the process.
虽然听上去不可思议 专家们还是认为可以
Impossible as it may sound, experts think there may be...
存在穿越虫洞的通道
a way to travel through a wormhole...
让人身临其境
and live to tell about it.
原则上 你完全可以
In principle, you can go right through...
前往另一个平行宇宙
to another parallel universe.
如果你再次穿越
If you go through again...
你就会抵达又一个平行宇宙
you wind up on yet another parallel universe.
要是你一而再 再而三地穿越
And if you go again and again and again...
你会在平行宇宙中倒来倒去
you wind up on repeated parallel universes.
这好像是进入了电梯 按下了上行键
It's like going into an elevator and hitting the "up" button.
每个楼面就像是一个宇宙
Each floor looks like a universe.
再次 不管怎样 有一个重大障碍
Once again, however, there is a major drawback.
一个问题就是你并不知道自己会到什么地方
One problem is you don't know where you're going to wind up.
你可能会达到一个恒星的中心
You'll wind up in a middle of a star...
有可能抵达一个行星的中心
wind up in the middle of a planet.
有可能最终证明 对于个人来说
It may ultimately prove impossible for individuals...
穿越通往平行宇宙的门户是不可能的
to pass through a portal to a parallel universe...
但是有可能成为拯救人类的另一个渠道
but there may be another way to save humankind.
如果通道非常小 比如 只有原子那么大
If the gateway is very small, like, for example, atomic in size...
也许我们要做的就是送出种子 纳米机器人
perhaps what we should do is send a seed, a nanobot...
微机器人 穿越通道
a microscopic robot through the gateway...
携带DNA 携带所有的信息
containing the DNA, containing all the information...
那是在宇宙的另一头创造新生命所必不可少的
necessary to create a new civilization on the other side of the universe.
我们究竟要关注什么?
Where do we see that in nature?
想想树木
Think of a tree.
树木会产生种子
A tree creates a seed.
种子包含了DNA 到处播撒
The seed contains the DNA that it shoots out in all directions...
尽可能生出新的树木
capable of creating a new tree.
想法就是假如一个发达的文明
The idea is that if an advanced civilization...
在将来能够收集足够强大的激光束的话
in the future could assemble enough high-energy laser beams...
理论上 他们也能够在时空结构上烧出一个窟窿
they could, in theory, burn a hole in the fabric of space-time.
那是非常困难的
It's very difficult.
但是我们物理学家计算出
But we physicists have calculated that if you concentrate...
只要你将巨大的能量集中到一点
enormous energy at a single point...
达到所谓的普朗克能量
to attain something called the Planck energy...
终极能量
the ultimate energy...
时空本身将会变得不稳定
space and time itseIfbecome unstable.
小泡泡开始形成小泡泡
Little bubbles begin to form...
那或许就是通往
little bubbles that are perhaps portals...
另一个宇宙的门户
gateways to another universe.
这样 微型宇宙舱或微机器人
In this way, a microscopic pod or nanobot...
携带着人类的DNA 我们这个世界的宇宙密码
containing humanity's DNA and the cosmic code of our world...
就可被输送到一个平行宇宙里
can be transported to a parallel universe.
面对灭绝
Faced with extinction...
这可能是人类最后的希望所在
this could be humanity's last great hope.
如果我们无法做到 那就意味着宇宙的终结
Ifwe can't do it, it means the death of the universe.
但是如果这个伟大的壮举得以实现
But if this incredible feat is achieved...
我们整个宇宙将得以复活
our entire universe would be resurrected...
就像凤凰涅磐 绝处逢生
and, like a phoenix, rise from the ashes.
换句话说 你是在扮演上帝
In other words, you are playing God.
这个奇妙的想法
This fantastic idea...
就像是宇宙iPod的重播键
like the replay button on the universal iPod...
可以将人类历史的宇宙协奏曲
could reset the cosmic concerto of human history...
回到起点
back to the beginning.
至少有些物种几乎肯定会存活下去
At least some kinds almost certainly exist.
或许其它物种也会存活下去
Maybe the other kinds exist as well.
我们只是不知道而已
We just don't know.
只有到那时 也许 我们知道有平行的宇宙
Only then, perhaps, will we be certain that there are parallel universes.